## **Jarrett Totton**

 Q Canada
 ■ jarrett.totton@gmail.com
 □ 506-663-5388
 □ linkedin.com/in/jarretttotton/
 ■ github.com/jtgis

### **SUMMARY**

Experienced Geographic Information Systems Analyst and Computer Science student with a demonstrated history of working in the information technology and natural resources industry. Skilled in ArcGIS, Python, Relational Databases, SQL, UAV Data Collection, QGIS, LiDAR, and Photogrammetry.

### **EXPERIENCE**

### Geographic Information Systems Analyst | Canadian Forest Products LTD | September 2016 - Present

- · Lead role for the software, data, and users of Canfor Alberta geospatial information systems.
- · Created a system to automate and validate the creation of Spatial Data Directives submissions to Government of Alberta standards.
- · Implemented the framework to collect, store, process, analyze, and use 2D and 3D data collected by Remotely Piloted Aircraft Systems.
- $\cdot$  Reduced redundancies by combining and expanding existing datasets and reports to meet current and future needs, cutting data management tasks and mapping products to manage by 50%.
- · Creation of standard work procedures documents for common and recurring work.
- · Prioritizing and triaging of tasks during periods of high demand.
- · Interviewing, hiring, and supervision of student co-op staff.

## Geographic Information Systems / Forest Health Technician | Government of Alberta | March 2014 - September 2016

- · Managing and monitoring forest pests and diseases in the Grande Prairie Forest Area of Alberta.
- · Creating, posting, awarding, starting up, managing, and administering several high-value contracts throughout the year.
- · Development of different survey techniques and guidelines. GIS data creation, analysis, and cataloging.

### Geographic Information Systems Team Lead | Vieworx Geophoto Inc. | March 2013 - March 2014

- · Processed LiDAR and imagery data collected by field staff into client deliverables.
- · Collected and managed GIS base map data related to our clients' needs.
- · Implemented Python scripting to automate repetitive processing tasks, giving the ability to process more than one project at a time.
- · Explored and implemented new business opportunities related to delivering data to clients via smart devices and delivering enhanced imagery products.

### Survey Quality Inspector | Infinite Forestry Consulting | November 2011 - March 2014

- · Quality inspection of mountain pine beetle survey and control operations to ensure that operations were carried out to standards.
- · Creation of maps to locate and navigate to site locations using company GIS infrastructure.

### Forest Technologist | Apical Forestry Consulting | April 2012 - October 2012

- · Conducted surveys and other field activities related to data collection for silviculture, volume sampling, and herbicide operations.
- · Accurate data collection using specialized tools and equipment.

# Geographic Information Systems Technician | Government of New Brunswick | Fredericton, NB | August 2011 - November 2011

· Contract position to assist property tax assessment with managing of spatial datasets and reports.

Further Experience Available at linkedin.com/in/jarretttotton/

## **EDUCATION**

## **Bachelor of Science in Computing and Information Systems**

Athabasca University · Athabasca, Alberta · Present

#### Geomatics in the Workplace Certificate

Selkirk College · Castlegar, BC · 2019

### Advanced Diploma in Geographic Information Systems

New Brunswick Community College · Moncton, NB · 2011

## Forest, Fish, and Wildlife Technology

Maritime College of Forest Technology • Fredericton, NB • 2009

### **SKILLS**

GIS Software: ArcGIS Desktop, ArcGIS Pro, ESRI Model Builder, ArcGIS Online, ESRI Web AppBuilder, ESRI Portal, ESRI Collector, ESRI Survey123, QGIS, ESRI Arcpy, ESRI API, ArcGIS Server, ESRI Spatial Database Engine (ArcSDE)

Programming Languages: Intermediate Python, Intermediate SQL, Beginner JavaScript

Photogrammetry Software: Pix4d, Agisoft Metashape, Drone2Map, Drone Deploy, OpenDroneMap

LiDAR Software: Fusion, QT Modeler, LAStools

Certifications: Defensive Driving, First Aid, Transport Canada RPAS Pilot License, ATV Safety, WHMIS, Class 5 Driver's License, Restricted Operator Certificate-Aeronautical, Chainsaw Safety